Finding Aid for Eliza Maria Mosher papers, 1846-1934
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eliza Maria Mosher papers 1846-1934
Mosher, Eliza Maria, 1846-1928.
852016 Aa 2; UAm
Physician and first Dean of Women at University of Michigan. Correspondence, largely of a personal nature with her niece Sarah Searing; biographical information; scrapbooks with notes and letters about travels abroad; and photographs.
4.4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 1425 ) was the gift of Mrs. Sarah Mekeel Searing, the niece of Eliza Mosher. The collection came to the library in 1942 with subsequent additions in 1943-1944.
The collection is open to research.
Eliza Maria Mosher was born October 2, 1846 in Cayuga County, New York. After attending the New England Hospital for Women and Children, she enrolled at the University of Michigan Department of Medicine and Surgery, graduating in 1875. In 1877, after a year in private practice, she was made resident physician at the Massachusetts State Reformatory Prison for Women. She was later appointed superintendent. She taught for a time at Wellesley College, then in 1883, she opened a private practice in Brooklyn, New York, but left this soon after to go to Vassar College as resident physician and professor of physiology and hygiene. In 1886, she returned to Brooklyn, then in 1896, she was offered both the position of dean of women at the University of Michigan and professor of hygiene, sanitation, and household economics. She left in 1902 to return to her Brooklyn practice. She died October 16, 1928.
The collection consists of materials accumulated by Dr. Mosher's niece Sarah Searing. It includes both letters received from Eliza to her niece, general family correspondence, and other Mosher materials which came into Sarah Searing's possession upon the death of Dr. Mosher. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Personal and biographical; Writings, speeches and lectures; Miscellaneous; Travel; Clippings and scrapbooks; Realia; and Photographs.
Subjects:
College administrators--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Michigan.; Mosher, Eliza Maria, 1846-1928.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery. Class of 1875.; University of Michigan. Office of Student Affairs.; Voyages and travels.; Women college administrators--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Aged persons.; Alaska.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Camping--1881-1890.; Children.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Families.; Interiors.; Mosher, Eliza Maria, 1846-1928.; Norway.; Offices.; Picnics.; Sewall, Lucy Ellen, 1837-1890.; Travel.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Volland Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Women.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Hazzard, Florence W. (Florence Woolsey); Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894.; Searing, Sarah.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - 1846-1908, 37 folders (Box 1)
  - 1909-1934 undated, 28 folders (Box 2)
  - Letter December 28, 1891, from Oliver Wendell Holmes, Boston (Box 2)
- Personal and biographical
  - Correspondence concerning sickness, death, and funeral of E.M. Mosher 1927-1929, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Copies of speeches (and related correspondence) in honor of E.M. Mosher at the 50th Anniversary celebration of her practice in medicine (Box 2)
  - Will, legal documents, and correspondence relating to her estate (Box 2)
  - Biographical and genealogical data on Mosher family, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Writings, speeches and lectures
  - Lecture outlines 1896-1902 (Box 3)
  - Mss. of speeches and addresses, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Notebook of reminiscences (Box 3)
  - Reprints of articles and tear sheets from other publications with articles by or about Dr. Mosher, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  (see also oversize folder for various certificates)
  - Book of Memories (Box 3)
  - Notes on Dr Mosher's meeting with Edwin Markham (Box 3)
  - Patents for her inventions (chairs, desks, etc.) (Box 3)
  - Questionnaire of U-M Alumnae Council with personal recollections of her college days (Box 3)
  - Various; include programs, calling cards, postcards, etc., 2 folders (Box 3)
- Travels
  - Trip to Alaska 1895 (Box 3)
    (typescript)
  - Trip to Norway 1899 (Box 3)
  - Trip to Italy and Switzerland 1902 (Box 3)
  - Trip to Sicily 1906 (Box 3)
  - European trip 1908 (Box 3)
    (diary and postcards)
  - Album of postcards, notes and letters from trips abroad, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Albums of postcards, notes and letters from trips abroad, 2 volumes (Box 4)
- Clippings and scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook concerning her book Health and Happiness, 1912-1913 (Box 4)
    (also include other clippings pertaining to her activities, 1896)
  - Scrapbook relating to her 50th anniversary as a doctor 1925, 1 volumes (Box 4)
  - Clippings relating to her 50th anniversary as a doctor 1925, 1 folders (Box 4)
  - Clippings re "Cleaner Brooklyn" committee work (Box 4)
  - Clippings re Dr. Mosher and the University of Michigan (Box 4)
  - Obituaries 1928 (Box 4)
  - Clippings relating to her career (Box 4)
- Realia
  - Marble name plate (Box 4)
  - Medals, pins, and membership buttons, 1 boxes (Box 4)
- Photographs
  (see also oversize folder UAm)
  - Family (Box 5)
  - Friends (Box 5)
  - Houses
    - Exterior (includes view of Volland Street, Ann Arbor) (Box 5)
    - Interior (Box 5)
  - Informal shots (Box 5)
  - Portraits
    - Early, middle (Box 5)
    - Late (Box 5)
  - Travel
    - Alaska 1895 (Box 5)
    - Norway (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan and New York (Box 5)